hello and welcome this is active
inference guest stream 79.1 on April 3rd
2024 we're here with Roto canai talking
about meta representations as
representations of processes we'll have
a presentation then a discussion so
thank you very much for joining and
looking forward to hearing the
presentation and talking
so go for it yes okay right yeah yeah
thank thank you very much for this
opportunity to uh present our recent
work U yeah and thank you for sporting
our very recent paper which uh just uh
uploaded preprint so uh so in this talk
I want to talk about what meta
representations are and but uh but to uh
explain my motivation I want to start
from my kind of frustration in uh
theories of Consciousness so um so a lot
of theories of Consciousness tend to be
described semantically and and then you
know for example like know in today's
talk I mainly focus on the uh higher
order theories of Consciousness but um
it kind of makes sense at the semantic
level but when we think about uh how we
can Implement uh such uh kind of high
level theories uh with uh new networks
uh we realize there are a lot of
uncertainties about how we might be able
to implement them but uh but I think
this is a you know something we now we
can call it like constructivist approach
so so by thinking about how to implement
uh theories uh we can actually reveal
vagueness and make uh the concepts uh
more um so more precise so so that's the
uh the main topic and so so as I said so
I want to talk about higher order
theories Consciousness maybe many of you
might have heard of it um but just uh
broadly speaking uh high order there is
of Consciousness uh claims that U mental
state is conscious uh not just by having
that processing but it becomes conscious
if it's represented by a higher order
mental state so by higher order mental
state or higher order
representation uh generally it mean
means it's a representation about
another representation so so intuitively
I think this makes sense so when uh so
for example when your part of your brain
is processing something red uh know
people ask whether that's sufficient for
conscious conscious experience of seeing
red but but when you have an additional
representation that represents that you
are processing something red so that
kind of meta representation seems to be
functionally related to awareness so
that kind of makes an intuitive sense
but but once we start thinking about how
we can implement this sort of meta
representation it's very
unclear what it really means um so so we
try to uh find a way uh
where we can sort of represent meta
representations but uh but let me
explain why it's difficult okay so this
is a very naive way to think about uh
constructing meta representation so
let's say you have a like image as an
input and then there's some processing
in the brain or deep new networks then
you can represent uh the the contents of
the input or image but but if you
transform this first of the
representation by another neuron Network
U that's like very naive way to
implement meta
representation but but with this uh you
can easily have like many meta
representations so know you uh let's say
like if we think of this as a uh like V
information processing in the brain
maybe know this could be the retina and
this this could be lgn this could be
V1 V2 and so on and but but this but
with this somehow like everything is
just a representation of the first input
so so somehow like this doesn't work or
like if you think this is enough for met
representation then like everything
needs a meta representation of something
else so
yeah so that seemed a little bit
strange and another way to conceive meta
representation is to think about
confidence so uh but in the context of
metacognition uh of and cognitive
Neuroscience we often take confidence
report from participants in an
experiment so for example like know we
could present some visuals stimulus and
then people report what they saw like
know if it's a color discrimination task
know they could say uh blue versus red
or something like that but then uh know
you use this first order information to
make a perceptual decision but also you
can report uh the confidence of seeing
that stimulus so so this is a probably a
bit better than just like very
simplistic uh sort of any transformation
as a met representation so but on the
other hand if we think about
implementing this this is a very simple
operation so people working in uh
artificial neuron networks uh easily use
something called Soft Max where know you
convert this kind of representation to
some sort of probability uh
interpretation so so basically if you
convert like activation
patterns of this layer
um to to that so that it normalized to
you know one uh then it is confidence so
so in a way this is just one very simple
uh transformation of first all the
representation so okay now maybe no this
is still meaningful when we think about
how the brain process this kind of
uncertainty uh but but but this may not
be at least it was not really satisfying
for me as a way to uh so uh
characterized met representations so the
the main uh solution we came up with
this idea
so uh so you can so so we always tended
to uh think about transforming first
order representation to something else
but but here what we are proposing is to
construct a representation of processes
rather than this kind of States so the
idea is okay so like like know any
neuron Network can be conceived as some
sort of uh function from input to Output
but but there's a way to present these
functions or processes so
so instead of re representing first of
the representation or we are proposing
we can if we represent this function f
to some met
representation uh you know know we can
have a potentially uh better
interpretation of meta representation
and because this makes a qualitative uh
difference
so but but maybe you know this might be
somehow confusing so I wanted to give
you an example using artificial neuron
networks so that's the main topic of the
[Music]
paper okay so here okay I just want to
briefly sort of introduce the concept of
Laten space or embedding uh for people
who are not familiar with this kind of
stuff so in artificial neural networks
uh there's a concept of encoder and
decoder and so for
example this is let's say you train an
auto encoder uh neur networks uh where
the input is an image and then output is
an image so so basically uh you want to
reconstruct input uh using encoder and
decoder but there's a low dimensional
bottleneck in the middle and and then
usually uh when you have this kind of
construction you find like interesting
like features where you know the states
in this uh the vector in this space
captures the you know like important
characteristics of the uh data set in
this case images so yeah so that's the
idea so so basically it's a know the
compress nice represent a of the data
set and but what we are proposing is to
create some sort of meta o coder where
the input and output are NE networks so
you
can
use a neur network uh which can be uh
parameterized
by or represented by the weights and
biases or you know you you can use like
many different ways to sort
of convert NE networks into some vectors
and then you reconstruct the ne Network
so so maybe you can already see this is
somewhat meta and so with this
construction uh you can have a
representation of newer networks so in
this case uh you know like know each
point in this space cor responds to some
sort of neur network or function so yeah
so so in a way this is a space of
functions uh parameterize some you know
like latent uh axis so so that's the
general idea so I hope you get the idea
so far yeah and so but from here uh know
I want to explain the actual experiment
we did and so this is a little bit more
detailed construction of what we did so
we first created a lot of encoders by
training all encoders for all kind of
different stimulat so example like in
one case uh you know let's say like we
trained this kind of uh first order new
know Network on just on uh parts or just
on flowers or or sometimes just know the
sign of dog barking and so on so like
each and know first order your network
is specialized in some kind of stimulus
category and we use both Visual and
audio stimula but but each network is
trained on just one type of
stimulus
but one category and so and then this
encoder uh uh can be represented as 1056
by
16 uh elements so like each column cores
okay so here like in the know first all
the lat space we have 16 dimensions and
then input image
56 uh pixels
and yeah
so basically know you can see this
number as the sort of you know
parameter for the new dispersal the new
network and then like each column
corresponds to okay so as you can see
that this is a very simple neur Network
so just one transformation right and
then um then know we took each of these
as the input as a filter and then know
we get like like this kind
of so okay so so this just one column
here is a filter in this network and
then we use this as input so so we know
we trained another Al encoder to
represent individual filters and then we
computed uh representation of this whole
network using these two networks so so
this may be slightly confusing but the
main thing is uh we get uh
representation of a network at this
stage and then
we uh created another meta coder
uh using this kind of lat representation
of our like first Network so it might be
a little bit confusing compared to the
previous image but but this is more more
to deal with the technical aspect but
the main thing is uh we trained like a
lot of small networks on the specialized
stimulus category and then we try to get
representations of those Nets so so
that's the
idea okay and so then uh know we applied
uh like tne to visualize lat
representations um so here like all the
blue dots corespond to some visual
stimul some category and then the orange
uh they point correspond to some
auditory stimul so that clearly you can
see there's a separation between Visual
and the audio stimulate so that's kind
of interesting right so because this
suggests that when you have a meta
representation you can already tell
whether the network is specialized in
visual stimulus or auditory stimulus so
so that's a
um that's that's what we were uh excited
about yeah but also you might be able to
see like some clustering of same shapes
it might be a bit difficult to see this
this image but but there might be
something like you know like
some you might be able to tell whether
uh a network is specializing cars or
buses or things like that so so we
tested that uh
uh
by trying to predict the original data
set just by looking at the meta
representations
so yeah
so as you can see like there's a clear
separation between modalities but but
there's a little bit brighter like
diagonal Elements which suggests that
know sometimes we succeed in predicting
like really
specific uh stimulus category so so
that's uh that's really
exciting
um
yeah okay so so so based on this uh it
seems we can uh there's already some
information about the structure of the
weight of the network uh which tells us
about what kind of information they were
trained on Specialized
in that's an interesting observation but
also like we tried this in the original
weight space but in that case we cannot
really predict like which know category
of the network was trained on so so in
that sense you actually have to have
this kind of meta representation to uh
be able to make the all these
predictions okay so um but maybe one uh
crucial question is know why is it
possible um so
especially uh when we try to compare
like Vision versus audition U maybe the
key differences they may have different
kind of invariances or equiv variances U
so yeah so for example like you know in
images you know the
object uh category or labels do not
change if we make like know translation
or Chang in scale and so on so like the
the classical convolution neur networks
are kind of uh rely on like this kind of
uh
invariances and but but maybe for
auditory stimulate or you know if
you sort of move the know if you
translate the input image or the sound
differently so you
experience different kind of sounds and
also the identity of the sounds changes
so so there might be some modality
specific invariances so so that no so
maybe know after training a network they
learn to capture that kind of
invariances and meta representation may
also find this kind of uh representation
of invariances or equiv variances in the
structure of the weight so so that's our
current explanation why this
works okay and I'll come back to this
later so and um so so in a way um like
our experiment uh was also motivated by
the like
classical uh question of what it's like
to be about and U the interesting thing
is we don't so bats can do echolocation
of know by emitting sound and then
receiving sound but but but but they use
it for navigation so maybe it's it's
like vision for them but it's hard to
say like whether they are experiencing
visual Quia or auditory Quia so so we've
been know we want to answer that kind of
question eventually in Consciousness
research and uh so but but to uh
introduce uh an interesting context so U
so this is a a very exciting series of
research from uh uh American group in at
MIT in the 2000 and so maybe many of you
are already familiar with this
experiment but but they managed to do an
experiment where they rewired the uh
input from the retina to the uh auditory
cortex so yeah I think it's like really
amazing that they can actually do this
sort of thing but um yeah so but the U
the idea is
that their auditory cortex are developed
by receiving input uh from visual
images the data coming from the retina
and the interesting so they had several
of nature papers and they were all very
interesting but the one of the key
findings is that uh after uh auditory
cortex was kind of trained on visual
input their connectivity pattern looked
more like normal visual cortex so yeah
so this kind of so connectivity
to l connection to like other neurons
know prob with like similar uh like
orientation
properties and so so somehow their
connectivity seems to reflect the sort
of uh like statistics or structure in
the data they learned and uh but there's
an additional interesting experiment
Behavior Experiment they did and the the
main question they asked is whether they
see or hear the activation of this
rewired auditory Vortex and the short
answer to that is there the animals seem
to
see the
uh the know brain activities in the
rewired auditory cortex so that's like
very amazing result so
yeah so based on this I thought like
this could be a really useful way to
like think about whether we are you know
whether you know some activities or or
some new networks uh it's more like for
hearing or seeing and so yeah so that's
something I always wanted to ask
so yeah so maybe um you know I've been
thinking about like testing IIT uh using
this kind of visual versus auditory uh
Quia and yeah so the question is whether
we can tell whether a piece of Cortex is
visual or auditory just by looking at
their connectivity so of course you know
IIT is very difficult to apply and we
don't know yet whether I is true or not
but but this know know we we need to
think about how we can test implications
of IIT by Empirical
research okay so so this was know what I
was thinking originally so let's say you
know you take some you know like Anatomy
from visual cortex or auditory cortex
and
then there are like many techniques to
look at anatomical connections and
functional connections it's very still
very difficult to read out the weights
from the actual brain but but if we have
this uh we should be able to
compute uh information structures as
suggested by IIT and we can probably
match the structure to uh the report of
uh know V visual qua or auditory Quia so
that's the ideal experiment I wanted to
do but there are a lot of challenges so
the first one is in the actual brain
it's it's very difficult to have like
complete uh characterization of
anatomical connections and you know it's
also impossible to look at the no
caal uh patterns uh in the activation
from all the neurons in question so
that's that's very hard seems impossible
and another difficulty is the the
computation of five in 8 is very hard so
uh and yeah we've been also trying to
compute some surrogate of five or
earlier version of five but it's still
very hard if we want to compute five
from let's say 10,000 neuron so that's
that's prettyy hard and so and also
maybe a third thing is no how can we
match the structure of the report of
experience to the structure of
information so that's again a difficult
question so but this know with the uh
approach I showed you earlier uh we can
kind of uh replace some of the problems
so so instead of looking at the complete
anatomy of the human visual cortex and
human aary cortex we can
create sort of artificial neural
networks by training them on specific
stimulate or in this case like sounds
and images so that's uh no the great
thing about artificial new networks is
we can see all the weights and
connectivity patterns so of course you
know we don't know whether they're
conscious or not but but least know this
approach gives us something concrete to
work with yeah and another thing is uh
about uh Computing file in IIT uh we
can uh do something slightly different
so there's a really interesting paper by
mediano and colleagues where they
propose the concept of weak IIT so like
if you take the original IID it's um
yeah it has like both like mathematical
and philosophical aspect so so that's uh
my interpretation and but but if we can
use the uh mathematical implications or
know if we use by as a uh kind of index
of complexity or something then uh we
use IIT in a more pragmatic manner so so
that's their uh proposal weak IIT so I
think I think you know there there have
been like a lot of Empirical research
driven by IIT so I think that's a a good
thing but but here U what I'm proposing
is like more like conceptual IIT so so
in the
U uh meta representation work I
presented today I I also took some
inspiration from IIT as well so the idea
is like in IIT whether that know some
Network generates uh visual or auditory
CIA should be fully described in terms
of their connectivity patterns so so
that's a kind of conceptual implication
of IIT so but instead of applying the
mathematical formalisms of IID we just
use all encoder to find or embed uh
neural networks
uh in a a practical computationally
tractable manner so so so so I think
this kind of the conceptual IIT approach
could be also a useful way to make
progress in Consciousness
research okay so the final uh point so
so maybe one question is whether meta
representations uh as we presented today
actually exist in biological Brands so
that's Highly Questionable so for
example uh you know today I embedded new
networks just by uh the weights of first
order networks but but in in the brain
seems impossible to read out the weights
from other brain
region well it may not be impossible but
but it seems like very unlikely and so
there might so maybe in the brain there
might be a different mechanism to
achieve this so so instead of using
weights if you have like many sort of
input output pairs you can also uh
Constructor representation of that kind
of relationship so maybe without some
figure or or equations it might be uh a
bit difficult to understand this but but
let's say uh you have two brain regions
like you know V1 and
B5 and but if a third region receives
the input from both regions the third
region can learn to represent the pair
uh pair of representations so that kind
of meta representation may exist in the
brain and also know we've been thinking
how we may be able to find such
representations with f so that's a a
topic for a future study yeah and
another question is what what's the
point of having this kind of metal
representation so what what's the
functional role so our current interpret
ation is when you have this kind met
representation you can uh sort of
compare different networks or uh you can
have some sort of qualitative
characterization of first order networks
so let's say know you have uh meta
representation of uh know red neur red
color processing Network or or you could
have like know meta representation of
like many many different first your
networks but but then in this space you
know you can talk about whether two
processes are similar or different so
for example in the space you can say the
visual experiences are very different
from auditory experiences but within the
visual experiences there are many
different types of experiences and here
you know you can talk about the
distances and
similarities uh so maybe it's a bit
similar to
the idea of like what to V know where
words are embedded in a uh lat Vector
space and when you have that kind of
space you can actually have some
reasonable representations of semantics
of the words but but here if you embed
uh new networks you can have some sort
of semantic or representations of those
networks so so that might be the
potential functional role and so so in a
way like know this has like
very this already has a a flavor of
something like Quia so when we talk
about Quia we always compare certain
experiences to other experiences and we
can talk about what you know two
experiences are similar and so on so so
in that sense maybe you know this kind
of met representation might be very
important for us to be able to report
the qualitative aspects of our for
experience okay yeah that's all and
thank you very
much thank you
[Music]
awesome
cool great I wrote down some questions
and also anyone watching live can can
write
questions um
well thanks for sharing it and it's
definitely very striking finding about
the visual and the audio differing so
just kind of a preliminary question here
how was time handled in the audio
setting oh good question well we we just
converted the raw signal into an image
so it's basically time and frequency U
so so that we can use the same network
for handing to different
modalities yeah interesting because it's
also a difference between those two
features and it made me wonder about
video video chatting or watching a video
perhaps as being a meta
representation with audio and
visual because if there's like a lag or
if there's a disconnect or any other
number of
relations it can um be noticeable as a
contrast like oh they're talking louder
than it looks like they're
talking or something like that so I mean
have you looked at that kind of fusion
or how could you look at it with the
architecture that you had here oh that's
a great question so no we we have very
simplistic architecture you know since
this was just a pereral concept but um
yeah so but but I think uh you know in
the brain we must have like really uh
multimodal representations at the same
time and so that way uh we should be
able to compare different experiences at
the same time and so so that that's
where we get somehow close to the idea
of global workspace so um yeah
so we we are not
directly you know addressing your
question but uh but we are you know on
on a separate project we are actually uh
training Global workspace like new
networks so that you know they learn
kind of multimodel
representations and uh also so in that
context
uh we believe it's very important to
look at the latent space structures from
different modalities and then see how
they related to each other so with uh
with Ru V uh we wrote a paper in Trend
in Neuroscience where we propos that
Global
workspace maybe uh can share lat and
space across different specialized
modules so yeah so so I think that part
is also like important uh like next step
to sort of uh to understand uh theories
of Consciousness from the perspective of
deep
[Music]
learning
interesting uh I I found it also very
interesting how you began with the
uncertainty estimate because in active
inference a lot gets low loed onto
uncertainty estimates of different
parameters and that made me think about
for a uh yeah thanks for the side it
made me think about for if you only have
two
parameters to encode then you can encode
like the mean and the
variance however with the neural network
autoencoder concept you could project
down to just two or could be more
and so then there's a much richer pallet
for and more bandwidth than just a
statistical distribution even though
it's also composed of statistical
distributions but the minimal and the
simplest and like the kind of most
essential is really the statistical
single distribution but this is
basically just talking about the
connectivity of multiple
[Music]
distributions yeah that's an interesting
on
[Music]
um yeah I guess the maybe crucial
question is whether and how
uncertainties are represented in the
brain so like when we think of
uncertainty estimation in terms of the
two parameters uh you know that's kind
of mathematical notion but uh the
uncertainties Maybe you know proba we
don't use just a single neuron to
represent whole uncertainty so so there
might be also population representation
for uncertainty so so in the actual
implementation in the brain um yeah you
may actually use like many neurons as
well but I've been also like really
interested in the this topic and
especially uh like uncertainty
estimation
in the uh thamus so no
my friend and colleague uh called comra
he found
a like uncertainty estimation neurons in
the Piner in the thamas for visual
experiences so I thought that was like
really and cool study and I thought you
know there seems to be like a close link
between having high
confidence and conscious experience so
so I thought know this might be like
like a really key ingredient but but
somehow like when we think about
uncertainty in terms of deep learnings
it it's kind
of it seems like very trivial so I feel
like there's a gap there
[Music]
um that's very
interesting there's a lot of ways to go
with that um in the the last two points
that you had up there you return to this
kind of functionalist question or at
least just perspective like what is it
doing so that made me wonder when you
look at the meta representations for the
networks you construct do they seem to
convey something like summary statistics
of the network
like the the spareness overall of the
connection or like some kind of network
descriptions you also mention the
differences in the stimuli type so like
does the what parts of the represent of
the meta representation
reflect what the network is and then
also like what it does input output
wise uh great yeah so we we don't know
really what's in the meta
representations of our
uh networks um but but maybe
this slide might be relevant so uh so
each new network the first order NE
network uh tries to find the good basis
functions or kind of good filters so
that they can efficiently encode the
images or sounds and uh but but they
they really come from from the
statistical patterns in the stimulus so
so that so that should be
somehow reflected in the know weight
structure
so so that may be related to know this
kind of invariances or equiv variances
uh that that's our speculation but but
also you know for like like really
specific type of things so for example
like these are all like different kind
of specific stimulus that maybe this is
air conditioning or car sound and so on
so so they may have like really
specific uh sort of
structure um so so then they may be
embedded in the new networks but the
interesting thing is when you train a
new network uh you get different things
every time
uh but but they have something common
across every training but on the surface
they look very different right so yeah
but but but
across the results of many different
training uh different networks trained
on the same stimulus there is something
common across them and so so that's the
kind of features we wanted to so capture
with metal encoders
Okay this may be reading too much into
the image but the um it's all V for
visual a for audio oh yeah yeah that's
that's right yeah explain it the the big
off diagonal blocks are just the
differences between the audio and visual
that are solid purple but then um and
then um the audio stimuli has more a
little bit with other audio but then
like in the visual it's I don't know
it's like related to the syllable
air so it's kind of like a natural
Association even though it wasn't
trained or maybe just cuz it's on a
diagonal
uh yeah there might be some bias oh yeah
this so this one yeah somehow the kind
know predictor thought like all the
images come from this one um
yeah but it seems like you know from
this figure like a different audio
stimul are very distinct whereas like in
visual things they seem kind of simar
yeah but probably the but this may be
more uh due to like technical
constraints so so here we have to use
like really like small patches so so
maybe you know
like instead of looking at object
categories per se maybe those networks
looked at the texture Parts across
different categories so there may be
still some information but uh but maybe
they're not very specific the IND c h
yeah I think I mean you're you're
shooting for the moon with a
Consciousness component but even making
simpler Networks to understand what
aspects Laten spaces learn is a very
useful method that I think this provides
a strong example
of yeah yeah I hope to so and but also I
know since we work in the domain of uh
like AI research as well uh we
encountered something called mechanistic
interpretability it's a kind of field of
where research where people try to
understand what's happening inside NE
networks because you know like people
claim a deep learning is blackbox and we
don't understand what's going on inside
but but but I think eventually we want
to understand what's happening in your
networks as well and the it should be
still uh easier compared to understand
in the brain so know maybe you know in
the context of idea I talked about this
a little bit but in deep learning we
know all the weights we can do like any
experiments we can do ablation or know
we can look at the function of part of
the
network and and we can you know give
them millions of Trials so so it's like
a ideal experimental setup for
neuroscientists and so if we don't
understand uh deep learning your
networks it's hopeless to understand the
brain because know it's much harder to
do experiments in the brain we cannot
know the weights and connectivity so we
we only have very limited access to the
actual material so so in a way we can
practice how to understand systems uh
using a simple neuron networks and then
try to sort of use that experience to
understand the brand so I think that
kind of coperation is potentially very
interesting yeah very well said um it
reminds me of some work by Jonas and
cording from 2017 the paper called could
a neuroscientist understand a
microprocessor and they had an in silico
simulation of a whole microprocessor
doing different operations so they could
do the lesions and the double lesions
make all the recordings MH and so that
kind of revealed on one hand the
limitations of different methods that
people often use to ascribe function to
the brain however there's always this
component where it's like well maybe
that's just because the processor is a
weird architecture or because the
operations that they do are very
synthetic and they don't really have a
natural component whereas when you're
proposing that the base neural networks
must deal with the symmetries of audio
visual and so on it's the kinds of
challenges that organisms actually have
to solve with nervous systems as opposed
to being
software which could have been written
in an arbitrary
way and so the results are a little bit
different but it kind of makes the
proof points which is that to have the
in silico version that you can do the
digital simulations on can help you
identify like where your studies are
well powerered or not and do all these
other useful functions even if they
don't directly answer the question
itself yeah yeah I'm also a big fan of
that like cing paper so I think I think
uh know that uh yeah yeah they made a
really important point so even if we
have access to all the things you know
we still may not understand it and uh
and it's hard to say whether you know
the
organic systems are easier to understand
compared to synthetic systems
so well I guess we know we just don't
know
but yeah but but without making any
assumption I think it's just very hard
to sort of uh understand any computation
happening happening in many different
scales uh not just in the brain but
inside
individual cells or maybe at the smaller
scale or you know larger scale like
Galaxy and so yeah I think we still like
the science to connect physics to
computation
so so on a different paper uh we also
propos something called
universality so the idea is uh
well so so the point is a theory of
Consciousness should be also Universal
in the sense that we can apply it to
non-biological brains so like a lot of
times people ask whether current llms
are conscious or not and but it's kind
of it depends on the theory you
subscribe to so but the current theories
like U higher order Theory or Global
workspace Theory uh do not tell us
whether know AI are conscious or not but
I think the reason is uh we need to
Define theories based on some physical
system so U what so for example it's
hard to say whether a neur artia neural
network has a global workspace we can we
have those Concepts but but but when we
try to analyze physical systems and then
try to see whether there's a global
workspace inside it's it's very hard so
you know we we need
to
uh make such theories uh universally
applicable so that you know they they
can tell us about know computations
happening at many different scales
correspond to you know the concept in
those
theories
yeah that
definitely uh kind of calls back to the
alien
slide and if we had a tissue sample with
only the static topology with no
function what could be
assessed um on a different note um
inactive inference I mean half of it is
action so when we're thinking about
variational autoencoders and the
transformation um from observations like
down into State spaces often that's in
terms of the policy rather than only a
compression which is kind of like a sens
making and reverse sense making
layer that's the predictive coding
predictive processing Origins and then
also to bring in the action
representations so that's kind of like
being able to distinguish the primary
audio and the primary visual from the
motor
cores and those may have very
simple or very um sophisticated
representations but they're also ones
that could be directly correlated with
like bodily movement or muscle activity
rather than being correlated at some
level if you go that way like with
something can't
measure yeah um yeah I think you know
like here like we only talk about
sensory experience but but but like you
said I think some of the
meaning uh of sensor experience comes
from action or in relation to your body
so for example uh you know without body
know there's no up or down left or right
so there's no Direction but but but you
get this kind of
know so Direction in the visual image or
reactivity your body for example and so
and also maybe you get uh kind of
representations related to affordances
so whether something is actionable that
also you know relies on some combination
of sort of action and extensor
representations yeah I think of it's
very interesting to think about how we
can extend our current Research into you
know more like
agent uh based uh
architecture that makes me think of um
the possibility that the meta
representations could be higher
judgments whether those are experienced
so like a a very cross modal judgment
would be like can a human make
this and then that could be asked across
modalities or could reflect multiple
modalities but it it it it has to draw
information
from also not just the sensory data but
like
other kinds of
memory
yeah it connects with with the broader
cognitive modeling and the agent
architecture whereas here it's really
reducing it to just the streams of
vision and audio which is the right
starting place and then there's going to
be other streams that aren't just the
sensory oh okay yeah that's a great
comment so this reminded me of the the
something I I had in mind and forgot to
mention
so we we are thinking of this kind of
met representation as one of the modules
attached to the global workspace so when
you have something like Global
workspace you know you want to use
functions not just from like sensory
inputs but you want to combine that act
with action reward and so on and
so in
principle okay so we want to use
representations of potential actions or
even like mental operations so like you
know adding two numbers is a kind of
mental action so when you try so so we
are actually like thinking about
connecting like this kind of met
representation to general intelligence
so when you are have a new program know
you have a representation of the task
and but but to solve a new task you want
to find a potential combination of you
know specialized modules you can use to
solve that task
so so so in a way you
know this kind meta representation can
be used to match the tools you have in
your brain with the current tast so so
in that two box you don't just have this
kind of visual uh representations but
but you may also want to use potential
future actions you can use so so but but
you can also use the same meta
representation approach to represent the
reperat of actions you can make so so
that's a know that's the
connection
H hm
yeah potentially in the active inference
model like you had the slices with the
different filters
MH the B Matrix in active inference or
just the transition matrix it's the
policy dependent transitions on the
world so that's kind of like the policy
dependent filter
applied yeah yeah yeah yeah oh yeah
that's a yeah good connection too yeah
and then also on the thalmus
I'm not familiar with the mamal neuro
Anatomy very much but when you said that
Clarity was important did you mean
like
what um yeah
so so I think a lot of interest uh in
confidence or met cognition comes from
the literature blind sight or blind
sight
like uh phenomena and so it seems like
even when you
have you have the ability to report
these stimulus without confidence know
you report no you didn't see it right so
so it
seems you know this kind of confidence
is
expressedly uh present in the brain so
for example like in the thamus and but
so when you de activate those neurons
somehow you know at least you know in
monkeys they lose the confidence as they
so in terms of confidence rating they
seem to become like Blindside patients
so so so in in my introduction I kind of
criticize the kind of Simplicity of
confidence as met
representation but but at the same time
in the literature of Consciousness
research it's also very important right
so somehow like without confidence uh
know you don't like really report it but
but I think maybe you know we need to
have like further studies about how
confidence or like lack of confidence
changes the way information enters
something like Global workspace or I
don't know some stage of Consciousness
so but I think that's like really likely
in the context of like know Precision
waiting and stuff right so
without confidence maybe confidence
works as a way for way to get
information to something like Global
workspace I don't know maybe I talk
about global workspace too much
but yeah I think it's a good way to like
think about systems yeah I I agree there
these are just like kind of the labels
and the the models that can then be
applied so what that made me think of
was
the again an active inference if we're
thinking about attention or Precision
confidence it's usually just one
variable in the minimal case just
changing the variance on a statistical
distribution latent spaces makes it much
richer um so then let's just think about
what sources are we paying attention to
which sources if are we allowing to like
ignite the global workspace or have more
of a percolating effect and then there
could be like it's like the dinner party
problem so one part of the problem is
just distinguishing and interpreting the
sounds so that might be a simpler like
left side louder or quieter and or or
moving to something like that but then
you would have a higher order evaluation
space with like this
person you can trust on this topic and
that topic but not this one and vice
versa here so that's invoking more of
the world
model and then that could
control to what extent different things
that those people said after they'd been
parsed out so like the primary sensory
mapping is simpler because this is just
a very sensor actuator type problem
whereas the higher order Laten bases
could be just very
large
oh yeah I guess maybe for like a simple
like presence versus absence kind of
judgment this
confidence may be like critical
for a stimulus to enter conscious
awareness uh whereas probably met
representation I talked about maybe more
related to sort of evaluation of the
quality of the content of Consciousness
so if we want to make comparisons across
like different sensory experiences you
know we need this kind of meta
representation I think that's a kind of
different aspect of
metacognition um yeah so I guess maybe
like like in like earlier days of
Consciousness research like people did a
lot of like present versus absent report
and it's all about detection but I think
detection is very different from kind of
qualitative assessment of experience and
so I think this uh kind of transition in
the focus of Consciousness research from
you know like present versus
absent uh report versus more like
structured report by comparing like two
experiences are similar or not so I know
uh now GS group um has been like know
developing this methods to sort of
capture for structure
so so I think you know we want to
understand why certain experiences feel
the way they do right and then that
those things seem to be very difficult
to approach but but by by looking you
know at you know sort of comparisons of
different experiences we seems to be
able to capture uh the overall structure
of the experience so so maybe you know
our meta
representation approach here is also
more about capturing more sort of
structured structure of the quality of
experience rather than you know whether
we consciously perceive something or
just subliminary process that
information that's a very interesting
point it's almost like the early Global
workspace and ignition were focused on
the
extent of the causal efficacy and The
Binding but it was sort of Left for
later what the semantics or the contents
were because the question was at least
from how I've seen it more like whether
it percolated to awareness or not or
like whether there was a binding or a a
reportable versus unreportable stimuli
MH and so it totally makes sense that
Within the space of of the
aware the question of how to bring it to
awareness is kind of already taken so
then it requires a much richer State
space like you have
here to even approach it because it's
just not an all or none question at this
point yeah yeah I agree yeah I think
that's a like really interesting
tradition although like I feel like we
haven't really solved this report
reportable versus unreportable question
yet because you know we still don't know
where Consciousness is really happening
in the brain but but I think
uh we need just um several different
approaches to you know tackle the same
Pro uh
problem cool well I guess sort of in
closing what are you going to continue
working on or what are you excited about
uh so we want
to uh do Empirical research uh based on
this uh so so I think we know here we
are proposing a new way to uh look at
meta representation so uh one thing we
are interested in doing is
to uh find whether such met
representations exist in the brain so
that's an open question but but we have
some ideas about how to try that and
another thing is this is kind of beyond
my ability but there might be a way to
do
this better using mathematical tools
so so intuitively you know so now now
like some people talk about category
theories and things like things like
that but so it seems like what we are
doing
is um can
be made more abstract and formalized so
that uh we can have kind of better
insight about what we are trying to do
so so here know what we did was kind of
like naive weight to express our thought
about met
representations but but
here yeah so we are kind of transforming
functions into an object so so basically
one function is a point in some
functional space and when this point in
functional space seems to
be uh somehow Rel to Quia so that's my
current intuition but but but I think uh
like in mathematics there must be useful
tools to sort of deal with this sort of
ideas I'm curious like if there's any
mathematician who who can of formulate
this nicely I think that would be an
interesting thing to do
next very interesting and also to the
little I know about it and people have
discussed it that is sort of a category
theoretic move to have a handle like a
point around a mapping so that you can
have the space of the models so you took
a very
constructivist
engineering empirical approach and then
it's an exciting open question like what
are the formal structures that
generalize that and then you could spin
up a million experiments just like the
one that you probably built by
hands and then learn from that pick up
that as a
point
yeah any last
comments oh I have just one
announcement which is this one
um yeah so I'm sorry about advertising
but but we have a the Consciousness
conference called assc I think that's
one of the like Main Consciousness
conferences and that's happening in
Tokyo this July so like if you're
interested please come I'm one of the
main
organizers that sounds awesome
cool thank you very much for this
presentation good luck with the work in
the conference and hope to talk to you
again yeah thank you was fun yeah see
you see you thank
you
for